Register of the Alexandre Georgievich Tarsaidze papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Alexandre Georgievich Tarsaidze papers
1648-1977
78055
Hoover Institution Archives
30 manuscript boxes, 7 oversize boxes, 39 envelopes, 1 album box, 11 motion picture film reels, 5 sound discs (28.5 linear feet)
Correspondence, speeches and writings, research notes, printed matter, photographs, engravings, lithographs, maps, and sound and video recordings relating to the history of Georgia (Transcaucasia), the Romanov family, Russian-American relations, and the Association of Russian Imperial Naval Officers in America. Includes photocopies of Romanov family letters, photographs of Russia during World War I by Donald C. Thompson, and a documentary film of Tsar Nicholas II.
Tarsaidze, Alexandre Georgievich, 1901-1978.
Thompson, Donald C.
Access
Collection is open for research.
Use copies of some motion picture film and all sound recordings in this collection are available for immediate access. To view other films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1978.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1901 Born, Tiflis, Russia, into family of old Georgian nobility
1918 Graduated, Imperial Naval Academy, Petrograd
1918-1921 Worked with Allied High Commissioner, Col. W. Haskell, in Tiflis
1921 Escaped from Bolsheviks to Constantinople Worked for American Relief Administration
1923-1941 Immigrated to the United States Worked for Matchabelli Perfumes, R. H. Macy Co., Parfum Chevalier Garde, and other retailers in cosmetic and jewelry business Member, Association of Former Russian Imperial Naval Officers Member, Georgian Society in the U.S.A. Director, Caucasian Society "Allaverdy"
1941-1944 Worked for U.S. Army intelligence
1944 Author, Morskoi Korpus za CHetvert' Veka, 1901-1925, N.Y.
1945-1958 Director of Public Relations, Serge Obolensky Associates
1958 Author, Czars and Presidents
1969 Author, CHetyre mifa
1977 Author, Katia: Wife Before God
1959-1978 Freelancer, public relations
1978 Died, New York City
Scope and Content of Collection
Correspondence, speeches and writings, research notes, printed matter, photographs, engravings, lithographs, maps, and sound and video recordings relating to the history of Georgia (Transcaucasia), the Romanov family, Russian-American relations, and the Association of Russian Imperial Naval Officers in America. Includes photocopies of Romanov family letters, photographs of Russia during World War I by Donald C. Thompson, and a documentary film of Tsar Nicholas II.
Alexander II, Emperor of Russia, 1818-1881.; Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia, 1868-1918.; Romanov, House of.; Association of Russian Imperial Naval Officers in America; Russians--United States.; Russia--Emigration and immigration.; World War, 1914-1918--Russia.; Georgia (Republic)--History.; Russia--Court and courtiers.; Russia--Foreign relations--United States.; United States--Foreign relations--Russia.; Motion pictures.; Video tapes.; Sound recordings.
- BIOGRAPHICAL FILE, 1851-1977 (Boxes 1-2)
  Scope and Contents note
  Correspondence, genealogical material, family papers and miscellaneous printed matter relating to the life, writings, and social activities of Alexandre Tarsaidze and the Eristov family, arranged alphabetically by physical form.
  - General, society
    Russian-American and other social events, especially charity.
    - Calling cards and personal notes (Box-folder 1: 1)
    - Programs and invitations, 1964-1976 (Box-folder 1: 2)
  - Business records
    - General
      - Ermitage Restaurant, 1960 (Box-folder 1: 3)
      - Southampton Hospital, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 1: 4)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1938-1976 (Box-folder 1: 5)
      - Publishing, 1956-1976 (Box-folder 1: 6)
    - Memoranda, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 1: 7)
  - Correspondence
    - Personal
      - Undated (Box-folder 1: 8)
      - 1943-1959 (Box-folder 1: 9)
      - 1960-1969 (Box-folder 1: 10)
      - 1970-1977 (Box-folder 1: 11)
    - Duke, A. B., 1977 (Box-folder 1: 12)
      Includes file on Panama Canal Treaty.
    - Eristov family, 1921-1970 (Box-folder 1: 13-14)
  - Genealogical material
    - L'Histoire et genealogie complete des Tarsaidj-Tarsaidze depuis XIII siecle de J-C., bound tearsheets, 1851-1916 (Box-folder 2: 1)
    - Eristov (Eristavi) family, miscellaneous material, typescript and handwritten, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 2: 2)
    - Eristov, Prince G., Moi Vospominaniia, 1875-1946, N.Y., 1954 (Box-folder 2: 3)
    - Tarsaidze, G., miscellaneous printed matter, 1957 (Box-folder 2: 4)
    - Family crest and stamp, undated (Box-folder 2: 5)
  - Personal and family documents
    - General (Box-folder 2: 6)
    - Clippings (Box-folder 2: 7)
    - Curricula vitae (Box-folder 2: 8)
    - Documents relating to lawsuit against Martini & Rossi Corp., 1965-1967 (Box-folder 2: 9)
- SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, 1936-1977 (Boxes 3-11)
  Books, articles, letters to the editor, and incidental writings of Alexandre Tarsaidze, arranged chronologically and by alphabetically by title thereunder.
  - General
    - Catalog, undated (Box-folder 3: 1-4)
      Includes émigré publications related to history, handwritten.
    - Catalog (Box-folder 4: 1-3)
    - Letters to the editor, typescript
      - Undated (Box-folder 5: 1)
      - 1940-1949 (Box-folder 5: 2)
      - 1950-1959 (Box-folder 5: 3)
      - 1960-1969 (Box-folder 5: 4)
      - 1973 (Box-folder 5: 5)
    - Notebooks, undated (Box-folder 5: 6-8)
    - Periodical press, writings, including articles and letters to the editor
      - Undated (Box-folder 5: 9)
      - 1936-1937 (Box-folder 5: 10)
      - 1940 (Box-folder 5: 11)
      - 1941 (Box-folder 5: 12)
      - 1943 (Box-folder 5: 13)
      - 1944 (Box-folder 5: 14)
      - 1945-1947 (Box-folder 6: 1-10)
        Includes "Rokovye dni."
      - 1948 (Box-folder 6: 11)
      - 1949 (Box-folder 6: 12-13)
      - 1950 (Box-folder 6: 14-15)
      - 1951 (Box-folder 7: 1)
      - 1952 (Box-folder 7: 2)
      - 1954 (Box-folder 7: 3)
      - 1955 (Box-folder 7: 4)
      - 1956 (Box-folder 7: 5)
      - 1957 (Box-folder 7: 6)
      - 1958 (Box-folder 7: 7)
      - 1959 (Box-folder 7: 8)
      - 1960-1961 (Box-folder 7: 9)
      - 1965 (Box-folder 7: 10)
      - 1966 (Box-folder 7: 11)
      - 1968 (Box-folder 7: 12)
      - 1970 (Box-folder 7: 13)
      - 1971 (Box-folder 7: 14)
      - 1973 (Box-folder 7: 15)
      - 1974 (Box-folder 7: 16)
      - 1975 (Box-folder 7: 17)
      - 1976 (Box-folder 7: 18)
      - 1977 (Box-folder 7: 19)
  - "Alexandrina and Alexander,", undated
    - Draft, typescript (Box-folder 7: 20)
    - Notes and correspondence (Box-folder 7: 21)
  - "Magdeburg Affair," outline for book, typescript, undated (Box-folder 7: 22)
  - Morskoi Korpus za chetvert' veka, printed copy, 1944. (Box-folder 7: 23)
  - "Fanny Lear"
    - Draft and research material, handwritten, undated (Box-folder 7: 24)
    - Legal agreements re publication, 1950 (Box-folder 7: 25)
  - Czars and Presidents, 1958
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1938-1959 (Box-folder 7: 26)
      - Business, 1957-1962 (Box-folder 7: 27)
    - Research material
      - Miscellany, 1862-1942 (Box-folder 7: 28)
        Includes material re Russian exploration of New Guinea and general correspondence.
      - Clippings
      - General (Box-folder 8: 1-3)
      - Explorers (Box-folder 8: 4)
      - Railroads, 1939-1950 (Box-folder 8: 5)
      - Russian diplomatic corps in the U.S., 1944 (Box-folder 8: 6)
      - Photographic reproductions, explorers (Box-folder 8: 7)
    - Legal contract for publication, 1957 (Box-folder 8: 8)
    - Drafts, typescript, undated (Box-folder 8: 9-10)
    - Film script, typescript draft, undated (Box-folder 8: 11)
    - Scrapbook of reviews and letters to the author, 1958 (Box-folder 8: 12)
  - Russia's Rich Husbands, reprints, 1955. (Box-folder 8: 13)
  - CHetyre mifa, [See also: SUBJECT FILE/World War I], 1969
    - Correspondence
      - Personal, 1965-1974 (Box-folder 9: 1)
      - Business, 1969-1970
        - General (Box-folder 9: 2)
        - Book orders (Box-folder 9: 3-7)
    - Draft, handwritten, undated (Box-folder 9: 8)
    - Advertisements and reviews (Box-folder 9: 9)
  - Katia: Wife Before God, 1977
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1949-1977 (Box-folder 9: 10)
      - Business, 1967-1970 (Box-folder 9: 11)
    - Research material
      - Unidentified (B. Nermi-Ergunov?), manuscript, undated (Box-folder 10: 1)
      - Gernet, L. von, memoirs and correspondence, typescript and handwritten, 1949 (Box-folder 10: 2)
      - Klap'e, O. de, "Kniaginia Mariia Tenisheva," tearsheet, undated (Box-folder 10: 3)
      - Nikitin, D., memoirs re "Goga" IUr'evskii, printed copy, 1945 (Box-folder 10: 4)
      - Genealogical material, typescript and handwritten, undated (Box-folder 10: 5)
      - Clippings and miscellany (Box-folder 10: 6-8)
        Includes material re Emperor Alexander II, Ekaterina Dolgorukova-IUr'evkaia and family.
      - Photo reproductions [same as above] (Box-folder 10: 9)
    - Drafts, typescript, undated (Box-folder 10: 10-14)
    - Drafts (Box-folder 11: 1-3)
    - Publicity material (Box-folder 11: 4)
- SUBJECT FILE, 1876-1977 (Boxes 11-30)
  Correspondence and printed matter relating to the Caucasus, Transcaucasus, and Russia. Includes material about the Imperial Russian Army, Navy, and Air Force, especially in World War I. Also includes material related to the Russian Imperial family and especially the film Emperor Nicholas II, Last Czar of Russia produced by A. Tarsaidze. Arranged alphabetically by subject.
  - Armenia
    - General, miscellaneous material on Mt. Ararat and Noah's Ark, 1967 (Box-folder 11: 5)
      Includes correspondence of A. Tarsaidze.
    - Printed matter
      - General, KHatissian, A., The Memoirs of a Mayor, tearsheets, undated (Box-folder 11: 6)
      - Clippings (Box-folder 11: 7)
  - Caucasus and Transcaucasus
    - Maps [See: OVERSIZE FILE]
    - Printed matter
      - General, Zakavkaz'e, Tiflis, 1907-1908 (Box-folder 11: 8)
      - Clippings (Box-folder 11: 9)
  - Georgia
    - General
      - Bagratids, Royal House of Georgia, printed matter [See also: Nicholas II/Romanov Family genealogy]
        - General
          - Lang, D., "Prince Ioan of Georgia and His 'Kalmasoba'", The American Slavic and East European Review, Reprint, 1953. (Box-folder 11: 10)
          - Tumanov, Prince K.
            - Miscellaneous offprints, 1947 (Box-folder 11: 11)
            - "Materialy k genealogii Bagratidov", Novik, Typescript, 1950. (Box-folder 11: 12)
            - "Kniaz'ia Bagration-Mukhranskie", Novik, Typescript, 1951. (Box-folder 11: 13)
            - "Poslednie tsari Imeretii i ikh potomstvo", Novik, Typescript, 1953. (Box-folder 11: 14)
        - Clippings (Box-folder 12: 1)
        - Genealogical records (Box-folder 12: 2)
      - Nobility and public figures, miscellany (Box-folder 12: 3-4)
        Includes genealogical material and writings of A. Tarsaidze. See also: Russia/Nobility.
      - Pretenders to the Georgian throne, "M. Grousinski," miscellaneous material, 1968 (Box-folder 12: 5)
    - Correspondence
      - General, 1949-1975 (Box-folder 12: 6)
      - Iraklii of Georgia, 1971 (Box-folder 12: 7)
      - Tumanov, Prince K., 1949-1958 (Box-folder 12: 8)
    - Letters to the editor, 1973 (Box-folder 12: 9)
    - Printed matter
      - General
        - Dadeshkeliani, I., The Autocephaly of the Orthodox Church of Georgia, 1922 (Box-folder 12: 10)
        - Mordovtsev, D., "ZHelezom i krov'iu", Novoe Russkoe Slovo, undated (Box-folder 12: 11)
        - Solov'ev, S., "Vostochnyi vopros 50 let nazad," Drevniia i novaia Rossiia, 1876 (Box-folder 12: 12)
      - Clippings, tearsheets and miscellany (Box-folder 12: 13-16)
  - Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia
    - Imperial Family
      - General, genealogy, undated (Box-folder 13: 1)
        Includes list of Romanovs in the U.S.
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1944-1975 (Box-folder 13: 2)
        - Romanov family, 1976 (Box-folder 13: 3)
      - Moving pictures, Emperor Nicholas II, Last Czar of Russia
        Also under titles Emperor Nicholas II - Last Monarch of Russia and Emperor Nicholas II.
        - Clippings, 1966-1975 (Box-folder 13: 4-5)
        - Correspondence
          - Personal
            - Eastman, Max, 1944 (Box-folder 13: 6)
            - Edward, Duke of Windsor and Wallace, Duchess of Windsor, 1968 (Box-folder 13: 7)
            - Lied, J. and viewing by Norwegian Royal family, 1958 (Box-folder 13: 8)
            - Massie, R. and S., 1968 (Box-folder 13: 9)
            - Mountbatten of Burma, Louis Mountbatten, 1957, 1967 (Box-folder 13: 10)
            - Post, Marjorie Merriweather, 1967-1972 (Box-folder 13: 11)
            - Tuchman, B., 1964 (Box-folder 13: 12)
            - Vladimir, Grand Duke of Russia and Madrid showing, 1966 (Box-folder 13: 13)
          - Business
            - General
              - 1944-1959 (Box-folder 13: 14)
              - 1961-1976 (Box-folder 13: 15)
            - Axelbank, Herman, 1969-1975 (Box-folder 13: 16)
            - Holmquist, N., AB Europa Film, 1970-1973 (Box-folder 13: 17)
        - Invitations, announcements and advertisements
          - General
            - Undated-1960 (Box-folder 14: 1)
            - 1961-1969 (Box-folder 14: 2)
            - 1971-1974 (Box-folder 14: 3)
            - 1975-1977 (Box-folder 14: 4)
          - Biarritz Benefit, France, 1968-1969 (Box-folder 14: 5)
        - Narration
          - Draft, typescript, undated (Box-folder 14: 6)
          - Notes, undated (Box-folder 14: 7)
          - Andrian, B., "Poslednie dni Imperatora Nikolaia Vtorogo," typescript, 1967 (Box-folder 14: 8)
          - Kalantar, M., narration for "Tsar Nicholas II and the Russian Revolution," typescript, undated (Box-folder 14: 9)
      - Printed matter
        - General
          - "A Christmas Hymn written by His Imperial Majesty Nicholas II...", San Francisco Examiner, 1903 (Box-folder 15: 1)
          - ZHizn'i TSarstvovanie Imperatora Nikolaia II, "Vestnik" Obshchestva Russkikh Veteranov Velikoi Voiny, 1970 (Box-folder 15: 2)
        - Clippings, tearsheets
          - Imperial family (Box-folder 15: 3-7)
            Includes memoirs about them.
          - Romanov family
            - General, including monarchism (Box-folder 15: 8-10)
            - Ol'ga Aleksandrovna, Grand Duchess, 1959-1960 (Box-folder 15: 11)
            - Nikolai Nikolaevich, Grand Duke (Box-folder 15: 12)
        - Photographic reproductions
          - Imperial family
            - General (Box-folder 15: 13-14)
              Includes Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia.
            - Alexandra, Consort of Nicholas II, Emperor of Russia (Box-folder 15: 15)
            - Alexis Nikolaevich (Box-folder 15: 16)
            - Olga, Tat'iana, Maria, Anastasia, Grand Duchesses of Russia (Box-folder 15: 17)
          - Romanov family (Box-folder 15: 18)
    - Abdication and exile of Nicholas II
      - Correspondence
        - General, including re publication of letters below, 1943-1970 (Box-folder 16: 1)
        - Erdeli, M., 1949 (Box-folder 16: 2)
      - Letters from TSarskoe Selo, Stavka and Tobol'sk to Margarita (Rita) Erdeli, nee KHitrovo
        - Typescript copies
          - Alexandra, Empress of Russia, 1916 July - 1918 January (Box-folder 16: 3)
          - Ol'ga, Grand Duchess, 1914 September - 1918 April (Box-folder 16: 4)
          - Tat'iana, Grand Duchess, 1916 - 1918 February (Box-folder 16: 5)
        - Facsimiles of above (Box-folder 16: 6)
      - Printed matter, journals, clippings, and tearsheets from emigre press, 1952-1957 (Box-folder 16: 7)
    - Death of Imperial Family
      - Correspondence, 1956 (Box-folder 16: 8)
      - Printed matter
        - Fashist, 1938 July (Box-folder 16: 9)
        - Clippings (Box-folder 16: 10-13)
    - Relics of Imperial Family
      - Correspondence, 1943-1971 (Box-folder 16: 14)
      - Printed matter
        - Tarsaidze, A., miscellaneous newspaper articles, 1958-1971 (Box-folder 16: 15)
        - Clippings and tearsheets, 1930-1958 (Box-folder 16: 16)
    - Rasputin
      - Correspondence, 1976 (Box-folder 16: 17)
      - Printed matter
        - General, Solovieff-Rasputine, M., Mon Pere Grigory Raspoutine, photocopy, 1925 (Box-folder 16: 18)
        - Clippings (Box-folder 17: 1-2)
        - Photographic reproductions (Box-folder 17: 3)
    - Pretenders
      - General
        - "Alexei," Michael Goleniewski, clippings (Box-folder 17: 4)
        - "Anastasia"
          - Correspondence, 1955-1968 (Box-folder 17: 5)
          - Clippings (Box-folder 17: 6)
      - Clippings (Box-folder 17: 7)
      - Correspondence, 1953-1976 (Box-folder 17: 8)
        Includes material re "Alexei," Michael Goleniewski.
  - Russia
    - General, printed matter
      - General
        - Fine Bindings from the Libraries of the Tzars of Russia, Plaza Book Auction Corp., N.Y., 1933 (Box-folder 17: 9)
        - Goebbels, J., Teoriia i praktika bol'shevizma, translation of speech delivered at Nurenberg, 1936 September (Box-folder 17: 10)
        - Okul'tizm i ioga, Asuncion, 1967 (Box-folder 17: 11)
        - Russia, Russian-American Semi-Monthly Magazine, 1944-1945 (Box-folder 17: 12)
          Includes articles by A. Tarsaidze.
      - Clippings (Box-folder 17: 13)
      - Notebooks (1-5), clippings from emigre and foreign press (Box 18)
        Includes material on monarchism, World War I, Civil War and Soviet Union. Book 5 includes material re female soldiers and sailors in Russian Army, 1922-1927.
      - Notebooks (6-8) (Box 19)
      - Notebooks (9-10) (Box-folder 20: 1)
      - Photographic reproductions, 1890s-1917
        - General (Box-folder 20: 2)
          Includes cities (St. Petersburg and Moscow) and Imperial palaces.
        - Political figures (Box-folder 20: 3)
        - Society figures (Box-folder 20: 4)
    - Air Force, printed matter
      - Clippings (Box-folder 20: 5)
      - Miscellany re G. Sikorsky, 1964-1972 (Box-folder 20: 6-8)
    - Army
      - General
        - Program-menus for official dinners of Guards regiments, 1874-1875 (Box-folder 20: 9)
        - Orders, decorations and coats of arms (Box-folder 20: 10)
      - Correspondence, 1964, 1974 (Box-folder 20: 11)
      - Printed matter
        - General
          - Danil'chenko, Col. P., Poslednii TSarskii smotr voiskam na Marsovom Pole, typescript, 1950 (Box-folder 20: 12)
          - KHolmnsen, Lieut.-Gen. I., Na voennoi sluzhbe v Rossii, N.Y., 1953 (Box-folder 20: 13)
          - Images de l'armée russe, 1683-1917, undated (Box-folder 20: 14)
          - Russkii Invalid, 1964, 1966, 1972 (Box-folder 20: 15)
          - Suvorovtsy, Izdanie Ob"edineniia b. kadet Suvorovskago Kadetskago Korpusa, undated (Box-folder 20: 16)
          - Vestnik kavalergardskoi sem'i, 1951-1969 (Box-folder 20: 17)
          - Voennaia Byl', 1968 November (Box-folder 20: 18)
          - Voenno-istoricheskii zhurnal, Moscow, 1964 (Box-folder 20: 19)
        - Clippings and tearsheets
          - General (Box-folder 21: 1)
          - Obituaries of former officers (Box-folder 21: 2)
        - Photographic reproductions (Box-folder 21: 3)
    - Automobiles, clippings (Box-folder 21: 4)
    - Civil War, printed matter [See also: Revolution of 1917]
      - General, Pervopokhodnik, 1971 (Box-folder 21: 5)
      - Clippings
        - General (Box-folder 21: 6)
        - Kolchak, Adm. A. (Box-folder 21: 7-8)
    - Corporal punishment and prisons
      - Clippings, 1965-1972 (Box-folder 21: 9)
      - Correspondence and letters to the editor, 1951-1974 (Box-folder 21: 10)
    - Cossacks, printed matter
      - General. Eliseev, F.
        - Nash polk v mesiatsy revoliutsii 1917-1918 godov, N.Y., 1961 (Box-folder 21: 11)
        - Pesni Kubanskikh Kazakov, 1960 (Box-folder 21: 12)
        - Reid Sotnika Gamaliia v Mesopotamii v mae 1916 goda, N.Y., 1957 (Box-folder 21: 13)
      - Clippings (Box-folder 21: 14)
    - Émigrés
      - Memoirs of A. Chicherin, typescript, undated (Box-folder 21: 15)
      - Printed matter
        - General, bicentennial of the U.S. (Box-folder 21: 16)
        - Clippings
          - Biographical material (Box-folder 21: 17)
          - Obituaries (Box-folder 21: 18)
    - Inventors, clippings [See also: SPEECHES AND WRITINGS/ General. Letters to the editor] (Box-folder 22: 1)
    - Jews in Russia
      - Correspondence, including letters to the editor, 1956-1965 (Box-folder 22: 2)
      - Clippings, 1939-1973 (Box-folder 22: 3)
    - Karaims, Zajanczkowski, A., "Karaims," printed copy [See also: PHOTOGRAPHS], undated (Box-folder 22: 4)
    - Money and government bonds, 1899-1924 (Box-folder 22: 5)
    - Music
      - "Baian," Obshchestvo peniia... v g. Rige, program, 1887. (Box-folder 22: 6)
      - Russian National Anthem and "Marsh gvardeiskago ekipazha," sheet music, undated (Box-folder 22: 7)
    - Navy [See also SPEECHES AND WRITINGS and OVERSIZE FILE]
      - General, Obshchestvo Russkikh Morskikh Ofitserov v Amerike
        - Bulletin, 1944, 1948, 1967, 1971, 1973, 1975-1977 (Box-folder 22: 8)
        - Correspondence of A. Tarsaidze, 1971-1973 (Box-folder 22: 9)
        - Lists of former Russian Imperial Naval officers, 1944, 1952 (Box-folder 22: 10)
        - Programs, invitations, and clippings related to social events, 1935-1975 (Box-folder 22: 11)
      - Correspondence
        - General, 1943-1976 (Box-folder 22: 12-13)
        - Letters to the editor, 1939-1969 (Box-folder 22: 14)
        - Material related to U.S.S. Whipple, 1950-1973 (Box-folder 22: 15)
      - Printed matter
        - General
          - Biulleten' Morskogo Uchilishcha Vypusk 1920, 1966, 1967 (Box-folder 22: 16)
          - Pravila dlia kadet Morskogo Ego Imperatorskago Vysochestva Naslednika TSesarevicha Kadetskago Korpusa, Sevastopol', 1916 (Box-folder 22: 17)
          - Imperial Navy uniforms, 19th century, lithographs (Box-folder 22: 18)
        - Clippings
          - General (Box-folder 23: 1-9)
          - Navy and Revolutions of 1905 and 1917 (Box-folder 23: 10-11)
          - South Pacific and Hawaiian Islands, 1935 (Box-folder 23: 12)
        - Photographic reproductions of Morskoi Korpus (Box-folder 23: 13)
    - Nobility
      - General, Sovereign Order of St. John of Jerusalem, Knights of Malta, miscellaneous material, 1967-1975 (Box-folder 24: 1)
      - Correspondence, including re imposters, 1957-1971 (Box-folder 24: 2)
      - Printed matter
        - General
          - Dvorianstvo, Paris, 1960, 1964-1965, 1969 (Box-folder 24: 3)
          - Novik. Istoriko-genealogicheskii ZHurnal, N. Pleshko ed., New York, 1942, 1948, 1949, 1951, 1952, 1958, 1959, 1961 (Box-folder 24: 4-6)
          - Russian Nobility Association in U.S.A., miscellaneous material, 1953 (Box-folder 24: 7)
          - Soiuz Dvorian, Paris, 1954, 1961, 1964 (Box-folder 24: 8)
          - Staryi Peterburg, iubileinyi sbornik vospominanii, 1953 (Box-folder 24: 9)
        - Clippings
          - General, including obituaries (Box-folder 25: 1)
          - Imposters (Box-folder 25: 2)
          - Social events (Box-folder 25: 3)
        - Genealogies
          - Obolensky, Princes
            - Pleshko, N., Russkoe Istoriko-Rodoslovnoe Obshchestvo v Amerike, 1959 (Box-folder 25: 4)